A single drop of blood.
A company worth nine billion dollars.
A young founder on the cover of every magazine,
hailed as the next Steve Jobs.
And underneath all of it,
a machine that did not
actually do what the world
was told it could do.
The story of Theranos is the most
famous fraud of the startup era —
and it ends with a question that hangs
over every bold promise ever made to investors:
when does selling a dream become a crime?
For this whole series, we have watched
the power of the state pressing against
one person — searching you, tracking you,
taking from you, following you home.
This final story turns
the camera completely around.
Here, it is one person
whose words reach everyone:
the investors who put
in hundreds of millions,
and the patients who trusted
their blood to a machine.
Over the next twelve minutes:
how Theranos rose, how it fell,
and what a jury decided
actually crossed the line
from ambition into fraud —
because that line, it turns out,
is narrower and stranger than you might think.
It begins in 2003, with a nineteen-year-old
who drops out of Stanford to start a company.
Her name is Elizabeth Holmes,
and her idea is genuinely seductive.
Today, a blood test means a needle,
a vial, a lab, a wait.
Holmes promised to erase all of that.
Her company, Theranos,
said its device — called
the Edison —
could run hundreds of tests from a single,
painless drop of blood
from your finger, quickly
and cheaply, maybe one day
in every drugstore and home.
If it were real, it would change medicine.
That "if" is the whole story.
And the world wanted it to be real.
Money poured in.
At its peak, around 2014, Theranos
was valued at roughly nine billion dollars,
briefly making Holmes a paper
billionaire and one
of the most celebrated founders in America.
Its board filled with famous names —
former statesmen and military leaders.
It struck a deal with the pharmacy chain
Walgreens to put its testing in some stores.
And the prestige fed on itself.
A board of household names made
the company look unimpeachable;
a soaring valuation made skeptics
look foolish for doubting.
Each famous believer became a reason
for the next person not to look too closely.
That is how a story, more than a product,
can carry a company for years.
Notice what made this so powerful.
It was not just a product; it was a story —
a brilliant young woman,
a revolutionary machine, a future
where a drop of blood could save your life.
Investors, reporters, and partners
all wanted to be part of it.
And a beautiful enough story
can make very smart
people stop asking the most basic question:
does the thing actually work?
In 2015, someone finally asked it in print.
A Wall Street Journal reporter,
John Carreyrou,
published an investigation built
on internal documents and whistleblowers.
What it reported was devastating.
The Edison did not work as advertised.
Behind the scenes, the investigation said,
Theranos was running
many of its blood tests not
on its own revolutionary device,
but on ordinary commercial machines
made by other companies —
the very kind of equipment
it claimed to have replaced.
And the finger-prick results it did
produce had serious accuracy problems.
For a tech demo,
unreliable results are an embarrassment.
For a medical test,
they are something else entirely —
because real people were making real
health decisions based on the numbers.
From there, the fall was fast.
Regulators moved in.
The Walgreens partnership ended.
In 2018, the Securities
and Exchange Commission charged
Holmes with fraud,
and she settled those civil charges
without admitting or denying wrongdoing —
paying a penalty
and accepting a ban
from leading a public company.
That same year, Theranos dissolved.
The nine-billion-dollar company
was worth nothing.
But a collapsed company and a civil
settlement are not the same as a crime.
The harder question —
the criminal one — was still coming.
Did Elizabeth Holmes simply fail
at something hard while believing in it?
Or did she knowingly deceive
the people who trusted her?
Those are not the same thing,
and the difference between them
is the difference between a sad
story and a prison sentence.
That question went to a federal court,
in the case United States v.
Holmes.
And to understand the verdict, you have
to understand what fraud actually is, legally.
Fraud is not failure.
It is not even lying in some loose,
everyday sense.
Criminal fraud requires intent to deceive —
proof that a person knowingly made
false statements to get something of value
from someone who relied on them.
A founder who genuinely
believes in a product
that does not pan out has
not committed a crime.
A founder who knows the truth and hides
it to keep the money flowing has.
The entire trial was a fight over which
of those describes Elizabeth Holmes.
At trial, the two sides told
that exact split-screen story.
Prosecutors argued that Holmes knew about
the device's failures and hid them,
pointing to internal results
and warnings she had received.
Her defense argued that she
was a true believer
who genuinely thought
the technology would work,
and that being wrong is not
the same as lying.
The jury's job was to decide,
count by count,
which story the evidence supported
beyond a reasonable doubt.
On January 3rd, 2022, the jury delivered
a verdict — and it was not a simple one.
It convicted Holmes on four
counts of fraud against investors:
one count of conspiracy,
and three counts of wire fraud,
for deceiving specific investors
who had put in large sums.
On those counts, the jury found
that she had crossed the line —
that she knowingly deceived
the people funding the company.
But on the counts that accused her of defrauding
patients, the jury found her not guilty.
And on three more investor counts,
the jurors could not
agree at all,
so the judge declared a mistrial on those.
Convicted on some, acquitted on others,
deadlocked on the rest.
It is tempting to read the patient
acquittals as a verdict
that the technology was fine,
or that no one was hurt.
It is not.
An acquittal means only
that the prosecution did not
prove those particular charges
beyond a reasonable doubt —
the highest bar in law —
not that the underlying conduct was harmless.
One juror later suggested the patient link
was simply harder to pin directly on Holmes.
And the contrast makes the point sharply:
Theranos's former president,
Ramesh Balwani — her business
and former romantic partner —
was tried separately,
and he was convicted on all
twelve counts, including
the patient counts,
and sentenced to nearly thirteen years.
As for Holmes:
in November 2022, she was sentenced to about
eleven years and three
months in federal prison.
The young woman once compared to Steve
Jobs was now a convicted fraudster —
but, precisely, a fraudster of investors,
on four specific counts proven to a jury.
So where, exactly,
is the line that Holmes crossed?
Because here is the uncomfortable truth:
a lot of what Theranos did looks
like ordinary startup behavior.
Founders pitch a future
that does not exist yet.
They project confidence
they do not fully feel.
"Fake it till you make it"
is practically a Silicon Valley slogan,
and most of the time
the law leaves it alone.
The line is intent and reliance.
Selling an ambitious vision is legal.
Knowingly telling people something false —
that a machine works
when you know it does not —
to get them to hand over money they
would not otherwise risk, is fraud.
The jury concluded that, with investors,
Holmes had done exactly that.
And there is a reason the stakes felt higher
here than in an ordinary bad investment.
A failed app costs you money.
A blood test that gives the wrong
answer can cost you a diagnosis.
That is why the patient
dimension haunted the whole
case, even where the specific counts did not
stick to Holmes —
and why Balwani's conviction
on those counts matters to the full picture.
Theranos is where this series ends,
and it is a fitting place —
because under every episode we have watched,
there has been one question,
wearing different costumes.
The police searching your pockets,
tracking your
phone, taking your property,
swabbing your cheek,
following you to your door — and now
a founder selling a miracle
that was not real.
Each time, the law's job was the same:
to find the line.
The line between a stop and an arrest.
Between identifying you
and investigating you.
Between a bold promise and a deliberate lie.
That is what all of these cases really are —
not dramatic stories about famous people,
but arguments about where a line falls,
as technology, money, and power keep moving it.
The Constitution does not draw
those lines once and for all.
It hands us the tools, and every generation
has to pick them up and draw them again.
Thank you for watching this series.
If you want to keep seeing how
a single case can redraw the rules we
all live by, this channel will keep
finding them — one line at a time.