Two thirty-two in the afternoon.
May the sixth
twenty-ten. For most of the
world nothing is happening.
And then in the space of a
few minutes the largest market
on earth begins to fall not drift not
slide fall as if the floor underneath
it has been taken away.
Nearly a thousand points gone.
Around a trillion dollars in value gone.
Shares in some of the most famous
companies in America trade for
a heartbeat at a single penny.
And then almost as fast as it fell it
comes back. The whole thing
lasts about thirty-six minutes.
By the end of the day the
experts will tell you the
market is fine. The
machine corrected itself.
But a question has been let
loose that will take years to
answer. Because something
moved that market.
And when they finally go looking
for what they will find a
man in a bedroom in a
suburb of London who did
not even like to leave the house.
This is the story of the
most mysterious crash in
market history and of the lonely
young man whose name would
end up attached to it.
It is a story about money
but it is not really about
greed. It is about a
machine so fast and so
clever that almost no
one fully understood it
and how close that machine
came to falling apart in front
of everyone in the middle
of an ordinary afternoon.
Over the next half hour we
are going to do three things.
We are going to show you how
a market this powerful could
be this fragile. We are
going to show you step by
step exactly what one trader did a
trick with a strange name
that you will understand
completely by the end.
And then we are going to ask
the question the whole case
really turns on.
Did one man break the stock
market Or did he only show
us how easily it could
break To understand what
happened in those thirty-six
minutes you have to forget what you
think a stock market looks like.
There are no men in coloured
jackets shouting and waving paper.
There haven't been not
really for a long time.
The modern market is not a place.
It is a network of machines in locked
climate-controlled rooms
trading with other machines
buying and selling not in
seconds but in millionths
of a second far faster
than any human eye could
ever follow. They are
called high-frequency
traders. Algorithms. Programs.
And in the years before our
story an arms race had broken
out among them not over
who was smartest but over
who was fastest. Firms
paid fortunes to place
their computers physically
closer to the exchange so
their orders would arrive a few
millionths of a second sooner.
In this market that head
start is the whole game.
And most of the time these machines
do something genuinely useful.
They stand ready to buy
when you want to sell and to
sell when you want to buy.
They are the water the market floats on.
Economists have a gentle
word for it liquidity.
The quiet promise that there is
always someone on the other side
of your trade so that whenever
you need to get out you
can. But here is the truth underneath that
promise the one almost
nobody likes to say out loud.
These machines are not loyal.
They feel no duty to be there.
They are not investors they
do not care what a company is
worth. They are reading
one thing the order
book the live scrolling
list of who wants to buy and
sell and at what price
and they are reacting
to it instantly automatically.
Feed them a picture of the
market and they will move on
it before a human could even blink.
And that is the quiet miracle
the whole market rests on
and its hidden weakness.
The order book is not just data.
It is a kind of collective
belief a shared picture
of what everyone else is about to do next.
The machines trust that picture
completely because trusting
it instantly is the only way to stay fast.
But a picture can be painted.
And a market that runs at
the speed of light on trust
in a picture can be fooled
at the speed of light too.
Which raises a dangerous
question one that in
twenty-ten almost no
one was asking out loud.
What if the picture were a
lie What if you could show
the machines something that
wasn't true a flood of buyers
that didn't exist a wall
of sellers who were never
really there and simply let
their own speed and logic
do the rest In a small
bedroom in west London
one man was not asking the question.
He had stopped asking it years before.
He was already living every
single day inside the answer.
His name is Navinder Singh Sarao.
He grows up in Hounslow on
the western edge of London
directly under the flight
path into Heathrow where
the planes pass overhead
every ninety seconds or so
close enough to rattle the
windows regular as a heartbeat.
He is brilliant with numbers
and uneasy with people.
Years later doctors will
diagnose him with severe autism.
He does not learn to
trade in a bank or a glass
tower in the city. He
learns it on a screen in
a back office and then at
home and he turns out to
be astonishingly good at it fast
fearless able to feel the
flow of the market the way
a kayaker feels a river
reading the current
the pull the places where
it is about to turn.
People who traded near him
describe it as a kind of genius.
And he could have had
all of it the office the
salary the city the noise.
He does not want them.
He wants the room. So
he trades from home from
the bedroom in his parents'
house in a tracksuit
the curtains often drawn
against the afternoon.
And there is something almost
unbearable about the picture
downstairs his mother is
making dinner upstairs
her son is moving more money
in a single afternoon than most
people will see in a lifetime.
And here is the detail that
everyone who meets him remembers
the detail that makes
this a tragedy and not
just a crime. He does not
seem to care about the money.
Not as a pose not as false modesty.
He doesn't buy the cars or
the house or the life the
money could have bought. People
who knew him describe a man trading
the way a child plays an
arcade game locked onto the
screen hour after hour
trying over and over to beat
his own high score. An autism
specialist will later put
it as plainly as it can
be put his lack of any
interest in the money he
earned was not an act.
It was simply who he was.
But to beat the high
score he wants an edge.
And he has become convinced
that the market is rigged not
against him personally but
by the fastest machines
the ones that always seem
to get there first the ones
that to him are skimming
a little from everyone
all day long simply
because they are quicker.
He doesn't want to join them.
He wants to beat them.
So he decides to fight the
machines on their own ground with
their own weapon speed.
He takes a piece of ordinary
commercial trading software
the kind anyone could buy and he begins to
rewrite it. What he builds
is simple to describe
and devastating to watch.
A program that can place
enormous orders and then
pull them back automatically in an instant
before any human and almost
any machine can take them.
Orders that look for a fraction
of a second completely real.
Orders that were never for
one moment meant to be filled.
There is a name for this a
name the law will eventually
use. They will call it spoofing.
Here is how it works.
And the genius of it the cruelty of it
is that once you see
it you cannot unsee it.
So watch closely. Picture
the order book again.
On one side everyone who
wants to buy and the prices
they will pay. On the
other everyone who wants
to sell and the prices they will accept.
The machines are watching
this book constantly and they
reason quite logically
if a huge new wall of
sellers suddenly appears
far bigger than everything
around it then the price is about to drop.
The smart move the safe
move is to sell now
to get out a half-second ahead
of everyone else before the fall.
So Sarao shows them a wall.
Using his program he places
sell orders so large they
dwarf everything else in
the book tens of millions of
dollars' worth stacked layered just above
the current price. The
machines see the wall.
They believe it because
they have no way not to.
And they do exactly what
their logic demands.
They begin to sell fast
to get ahead of the drop.
And the price begins to
fall pushed down not by
anyone actually selling
but by the simple fear that
selling is coming. And that is the moment.
As the price slides toward the
level where he secretly wants to
buy Sarao cancels the wall.
In the blink of an eye the
orders that frightened the whole
market simply vanish because they
were never meant to be filled.
They were a ghost. And in the
empty space they leave behind
at the low price his own ghost
created he buys. For real.
Then he turns the entire
thing upside down to sell.
Show a wall of buyers lift
the price pull the wall sell high.
Show a wall of sellers drop
the price pull the
wall buy low.
Again. And again.
And again not for a day but for years.
By his own later admission this
earns him at least twelve point
eight million dollars.
Regulators will say the true
figure across all his trading
was far higher. Think
about what that means.
He is in effect lying to the market not
in words but in orders.
And the market that vast rational
lightning-fast machine that holds
the savings of millions of people
believes him. Every single time.
And the strangest part is
how invisible it all is.
There is no broken window no alarm no
smoke just numbers appearing and
vanishing faster than thought
on screens in locked rooms.
To almost everyone watching
the market in those years
nothing looks wrong at all.
The wall goes up the wall
comes down and only the man
who built it ever knows
it was never really there.
For most of those years
almost no one even notices.
A single man in a single
bedroom is quietly leaning his
whole weight against the most
sophisticated financial system ever built.
And the system it turns out leans.
It bends right where he pushes.
The only question left
the one nobody has thought
to ask is what happens if one day he
leans on it at exactly the wrong moment.
May the sixth twenty-ten does
not begin as a catastrophe.
It begins as a nervous day.
On the other side of the world
Greece is sliding toward financial
collapse there are riots in
the streets of Athens on the
evening news and the markets
everywhere are jittery
on edge looking for a reason to be afraid.
Fear is already in the room.
It only needs a push.
Into that fear that morning Navinder
Sarao switches on his program.
Investigators will later say
that on this single day he places
modifies and cancels
orders worth billions of
dollars a vast ghost wall leaning
on the market on and off for hours.
But he is not alone.
And this is the part the simple
version of the story always
leaves out. Somewhere else entirely for
reasons that are completely
ordinary and completely legal a
large investment firm decides to sell
to hedge a position to protect itself.
It is an enormous order
seventy-five thousand
futures contracts more than
four billion dollars' worth
and it is fed into the
market not by a person but
by an algorithm of its own.
An algorithm given one
instruction sell and
sell quickly without much
regard for the price it
gets or the damage it
might do on the way down.
So now there are two great weights
pressing on the same fragile
market at the same moment.
One a careless giant selling
four billion dollars as fast
as it can. One a deliberate ghost leaning
and lying. And all around them the
high-frequency machines the
water the market floats on
are watching the order
book fill with sell sell
sell and they are beginning to flinch.
At two thirty-two in the
afternoon something gives.
The machines that promised
to always be there do
the one thing no one had
planned for the one thing the
whole system quietly depended on
them never doing. They
step back. All at once.
To protect themselves from a falling
market they simply stop buying.
And the floor disappears.
Now prices do not fall.
They collapse into a vacuum.
With almost no machines left
willing to catch them shares in
giant healthy world-famous
companies plunge toward nothing.
For a few astonishing seconds
you could have bought a share of
a company worth tens of billions
of dollars for a single penny
not because anything real had
changed about that company
not because of any news but
because for a few minutes
on the whole of the market
there was simply no one on
the other side. And it is
not only numbers on a screen.
All over the country ordinary
people have left standing
instructions with their brokers sell
automatically if my stock
ever falls below this price
small sensible safety nets
meant to protect them.
In those thirty-six minutes
as prices fall through the
floor those instructions fire all at once
selling people's savings into
the very bottom of the crash
at the worst prices of the day.
The panic of the machines
becomes for a few minutes the
real and lasting loss of people
who were not even watching.
And then the safeties trip.
Automatic circuit breakers
built for exactly this begin
to fire exchanges pause
the panic runs out of room.
Cautiously the machines come back.
The water returns. And
the market floats again
climbing back out of the hole
almost as violently as it fell
in. It is over.
A trillion dollars has
been lost and found inside
a single hour. And the most
powerful financial system on
earth has just learned something
about itself that it would very
much prefer not to know.
Afterward comes the autopsy.
And this is where the story
refuses to be simple where you
have to resist with both
hands the ending you want.
Because we want a villain.
A villain would be a relief.
The first official report months
later points mostly at the careless
giant that four-billion-dollar
sell program
dumped by an unthinking
algorithm into a market that
had grown too thin to absorb it.
It barely mentions a
trader in London at all.
Then other studies look harder
at the high-frequency machines
and reach a careful important conclusion
the machines did not
cause the crash but they
deepened it by all racing
for the exit at once
by demanding to get out first.
And then almost five years
later investigators trace the
ghost back to its source
to the bedroom in Hounslow.
They say his wall that morning
was part of the imbalance
that tipped the market over.
In their words he was
significantly responsible for the
order imbalances that
helped trigger the fall.
How they found him at all
is its own quiet story.
The ghost had left almost
no fingerprints his
orders had simply vanished the
instant they did their work.
It took years of patient effort
sifting back through the raw
data of that single
afternoon through billions of
messages to trace the
vanished orders through the
noise to one account and
one house in Hounslow.
The most mysterious crash
in market history was
unraveled in the end not by speed but by
someone slow and stubborn
enough to keep looking.
But notice the words they actually use.
Part of. Contributed to. Helped
to tip. Significantly responsible for the
imbalance. Not anywhere in any serious
account caused it alone.
Because the honest answer is
harder than a single villain
and far more frightening.
A careless four-billion-dollar sell order.
A swarm of machines all protecting
themselves at the same instant.
A world already sick
with fear over Greece.
And yes a ghost in the order book pushing
at exactly the wrong moment.
All of it together at
once on a market that had
quietly invisibly become too fast and too
fragile for anyone anywhere to fully see.
Which leaves us with the question
this whole story has been circling
from the very first second.
If a system this powerful
can be pushed to the edge of
collapse by a lie told in
orders that were never even
real then what exactly broke that day
The man who told the lie Or
the machine that could not
tell the difference between a
phantom and the truth The law
in the end does not get to
answer that with a shrug.
The law has to choose someone to hold.
And of all the forces in that
market on that afternoon the
algorithms the firms the
fear only one of them
was a person who had made
a choice and broken a rule
on purpose. And so the
law chooses the man.
In twenty-fifteen five
years after the crash
they finally come for him.
He is arrested at his parents'
house in London the same
house the same street under
the flight path and the
United States asks for him by name the
Hounslow day-trader the
headlines now say who
helped trigger a trillion-dollar
crash from his bedroom.
He fights the extradition for months.
He loses. And when
investigators finally open up
his life and look at what
is actually there they
find something almost unbearable.
The fortune the tens of
millions he had won from the
fastest machines on earth is
mostly gone. Not spent. Taken.
The man who could fool the most
sophisticated market ever built
had himself turned out
to be an easy mark he had
handed his money almost
all of it to con men
to bogus investments to
an outright fraud built to
part trusting people from their savings.
He had beaten the high score
over and over for years
and kept almost none of the points.
In twenty-sixteen he pleads guilty.
Not to causing the crash to two
specific crimes one count of wire fraud
and one count of spoofing.
He agrees to hand back nearly
thirteen million dollars.
And then he does something the
authorities did not have to ask
twice for. He cooperates
completely sitting
with them explaining his own
methods helping the people who
caught him understand the very
thing he had spent years perfecting.
There is a temptation telling
this to turn him into a folk
hero the lone genius who
beat the machines at their
own game. Resist that.
What he did broke the law
and he admitted it real money
moved and real people
somewhere were on the other
side of it. But there is
no honesty in making him a
monster either. The truth is smaller
and sadder a brilliant lonely man chasing
a number on a screen who
understood the rule he broke
better than almost anyone
and never seemed to grasp
or to care what the
number was actually worth.
And at his sentencing the prosecutors
do something genuinely rare.
They ask the judge for mercy.
They point to his cooperation.
And they point to the diagnosis the severe
autism that an expert testifies was woven
through the whole story that
made the money meaningless
to him and the game everything that
helps explain a man who could
read a global market like a
book and yet could be robbed
blind by the oldest tricks
in the world. He had faced
the real possibility of
years even a decade in an American prison.
In twenty-twenty the judge
sentences him to no further
prison at all. A single
year served at home.
In the bedroom more or less
where the whole thing began.
The money is gone. The program is gone.
And the man goes quietly back
to an ordinary house under the
flight path the planes
still passing overhead
every ninety seconds
regular as a heartbeat.
We wanted this story to have
a villain because a villain is
comforting. A villain
means the system was sound
and one bad man broke it
and now the bad man has
been caught and so we are safe.
But that is not quite what happened here.
What happened is that a lonely
man who did not care about
money playing a game in
his bedroom reached out one
finger and touched the
great machine of the market
and the machine for
thirty-six minutes shook.
He did not do it alone.
But he showed us more clearly
than any report ever could how
little it might take. And
the market is faster now than
it was that day. Faster and more automatic
and more sure of itself
than ever more machines
more speed more weight
resting on the quiet promise
that the water will always be there.
We are told it is rational.
We are told it is safe.
But somewhere inside it
still is the memory of
a single afternoon when the
most rational machine ever
built looked at a ghost and believed it.
So here is the question
we will leave you with.
The next time the floor
disappears and one day it will
who do you think will be
holding the ghost Thank you for
watching. If you want more
stories about the hidden machinery
that quietly runs our money
and our lives this is what
this channel does.
Subscribe and we will
see you in the next one.