You do it constantly. You tap "I
agree." You do not read it —
almost no one does . And buried
in that fine print, again and again,
is a single clause that can quietly
take away two of your most basic
legal rights: the right to take the
company to court, and the right to
join with everyone else they treated the
same way . In 2011, a fight
over about thirty
dollars turned that clause
into the law of the land .
The clause is an arbitration agreement. It
says that if you have a dispute,
you will not sue in a public
court — you will take it to
a private arbitrator, one customer at a
time. And it usually adds a second
piece: a class-action
waiver, a promise that
you will never band together with other
people who were harmed the same way
. This is one of the most
consequential and most
argued-about features of modern
American law, and
reasonable people strongly disagree
about whether it is fair. Over the
next twelve minutes:
the thirty-dollar case that
made it enforceable,
what the Court actually
decided, and the honest arguments on both
sides.
It starts with a couple in California,
Vincent and Liza Concepcion. They sign up
with AT&T for
cellphones advertised as "free."
Then the bill comes, and they have
been charged about thirty dollars in sales
tax on those "free" phones .
Thirty dollars. On its own, it is
nothing — no lawyer on earth takes
a thirty-dollar case. And that is exactly
the point that makes this story matter.
Because the Concepcions were not the only
customer charged that tax. If a company
charges thirty dollars too much to one
person, it is a rounding error. If
it charges thirty dollars too much to
millions of people, it is tens of
millions of dollars — and now it
is worth fighting .
The tool for that fight is the
class action: a
single lawsuit that bundles
together everyone with
the same small claim,
so that harms too tiny to sue
over individually can be challenged all at
once. The Concepcions wanted to bring one
.
But their AT&T contract said no. It
required any dispute to go to individual
arbitration, and it
specifically waived class actions
. So the legal question became: is
that waiver enforceable?
California had a rule
— from a case called Discover Bank
— that treated
these class-action waivers in
consumer contracts as
unconscionable, and refused to
enforce them. Under
California law, the Concepcions
could keep their class action .
AT&T argued that California rule had to
give way to a much older federal
law. And so a dispute over thirty
dollars in phone tax became a case
about who gets to decide whether you
can ever join a class action at
all.
To understand the case, you have to
understand two things: a 1925 law, and
one small, powerful sentence.
The 1925 law is the Federal Arbitration
Act. It was passed to make arbitration
agreements enforceable, reflecting
a federal policy that
favors arbitration — the idea that if
two parties agree
to resolve disputes privately,
courts should hold them to it .
For most of its life, that law
lived quietly. Then
companies began writing arbitration
clauses into the
everyday contracts ordinary people
sign — for phones, banks, credit cards,
and jobs .
And here is what makes them so
easy to miss. You do not sign
these clauses with a pen at a
desk. You accept them by activating a
phone, opening an account, clicking a box,
or showing up for your first day
of work. The law treats that as
a real agreement — and for the
most part, the terms are not up
for negotiation. It is take it or
leave it, and "leaving it" can mean
going without the service, or the job
.
The powerful sentence
is the class-action waiver.
Arbitration by itself
just changes the venue
— court versus a private arbitrator. The
waiver does something
more: it forces every
claim to be brought one person at
a time. And for the small, scattered
harms we just described, "one person at
a time" can mean, in practice, "no
one at all," because no individual claim
is large enough to pursue .
This is where honest people split, and
it is worth hearing both sides plainly.
Critics argue that
mandatory arbitration with class-action
waivers — what
they call "forced arbitration"
— can quietly close the courthouse door,
leaving widespread small
harms with no realistic
remedy, decided in
private proceedings that set
no public precedent .
Defenders argue the
opposite: that arbitration is
generally faster, cheaper,
and less formal than
a lawsuit, that the 1925 law reflects
a long-standing policy
of honoring agreements people
make, and that
individual claimants can sometimes
do as well or better than they
would in a crowded court . Those
empirical claims — about cost, speed, and
outcomes — are genuinely disputed, and we
are not going to pretend one side
has settled them. The case is about
who decides.
In 2011, the Supreme Court sided with
AT&T. By a vote of five to
four, it held that the Federal Arbitration
Act preempts California's rule — that a
state cannot refuse
to enforce a class-action
waiver just because it finds the waiver
unfair. If the
contract says individual arbitration,
individual arbitration it is .
The opinion was written by Justice Antonin
Scalia. A state rule that singles out
arbitration's class-action waivers
and blocks them, he
reasoned, stands as an obstacle to the
federal policy favoring
arbitration, and so it
cannot stand. The federal law wins .
Justice Stephen Breyer
wrote the dissent, and
it put the other half of the
problem into words. For claims worth only
a few dollars each, he argued, the
class action is often the only realistic
way to hold a large company accountable
at all. Take it away, and you
have not just changed the forum —
you may have ended the case before
it starts .
That five-to-four split did not settle the
country's mind, but it settled the law.
And seven years later, the Court extended
it into the one place most adults
spend their days: work. In Epic Systems
v. Lewis, in 2018, by another five-to-four
vote, with Justice
Neil Gorsuch writing, the
Court held that
employers, too, can require
employees to arbitrate
individually and waive class
or collective actions — and that doing
so does not violate federal labor law
. The same logic that governed your
phone contract now governed your job.
Epic was not a quiet decision either.
Justice Ruth Bader
Ginsburg wrote a forceful
dissent, arguing that
forcing employees to face
their employer one at a time ignored
the very reason federal law lets workers
act together — and she read part
of it aloud from the bench, a
step justices reserve for the rulings they
most strongly oppose .
So here is where it leaves you.
Mandatory arbitration clauses,
with class-action waivers, are
now a standard feature of American life
— in the contracts for your phone,
your bank account,
your streaming apps, and
very often your employment . You have
almost certainly agreed
to several of them,
by doing nothing more than using a
service or starting a job.
Whether that is a good thing depends
on which argument
you find more convincing,
and that is a real debate, not
a settled one . What is not
in dispute is the mechanism. Two ordinary
rights — to sue in open court,
and to join with others — are
now, for most people, waivable by a
sentence almost no one reads.
What can you actually do about it?
Honestly, not much in the moment —
the terms are rarely negotiable. But the
argument itself is
not over. Lawmakers, regulators,
and companies keep
fighting over where mandatory
arbitration should apply
and where it should
not, especially for the most serious kinds
of claims. The line this series keeps
chasing is, here too, still being drawn
.
And notice what makes this different from
everything else in this series. No officer
took anything. No
school punished anyone. The
power here was handed over voluntarily, in
the most ordinary act of modern life:
tapping a button to make a screen
go away.
A thirty-dollar charge on a "free" phone
ended up drawing one of the quietest
but widest lines in modern law —
the line between the rights you have
and the rights you can sign away
without realizing it . The Court did
not take those rights from you. It
said you were free to give them
up. The fine print did the rest.
We have now watched the state search
you, track you, take your property, and
police your speech — and watched you
hand over rights yourself, by contract. In
every case, the
same question keeps returning
in a new costume: where is the
line, and who gets to move it?
The next case
moves that question somewhere
more intimate than a phone or a
contract. Not what you carry, or what
you sign, but what is inside your
body. When the police arrest you —
before any trial, before any conviction —
can they take a sample of your
DNA, and keep it? That is next
time.