Right now, the phone in your pocket is
keeping a record of where you are. It
does it automatically, every few minutes, and it
sends that record to your carrier. In
2011, police used 127 days of one man's
location records to place him near a string
of robberies — and they got those records
without a warrant. The question that reached
the Supreme Court was simple and enormous: when
your phone tracks you, who does that trail
belong to?
We have spent two episodes watching the Court
draw the line of privacy — first on
a public sidewalk, then on the phone in
your pocket. Each time, the rule depended on
something you could point to: a body, a
device, an expectation you could see. But your
phone broke that logic. It exposes you constantly,
not because you chose to, but because that
is how the network works. Over the
next twelve minutes: the case that asked whether
decades of old privacy rules could survive a
device that follows you everywhere, and the line
the Court finally drew in the digital age.
In 2010 and 2011, a series of armed
robberies hit stores around Detroit, Michigan — electronics
shops and phone stores, hit by a rotating
crew. When the police arrested a suspect,
he confessed and gave them names and, crucially,
phone numbers of the men he said were
involved.
One of those numbers belonged to a man
named Timothy Carpenter.
To build their case, investigators did not need
to follow Carpenter or watch his house. They
went to his wireless carriers and asked for
something most people in 2011 did not know
existed: his cell-site location information.
Here is what that is. Every time your
phone connects to a tower — to send
a text, take a call, or just check
for messages in the background — the network
logs which tower it used. Those towers
cover known areas. String the records together over
days and weeks, and you do not just
get a few points. You get a map
of a person's movements, hour by hour.
The government obtained around 127 days of Carpenter's
records — almost 13,000 location points, about 12,898
in all, tracing where his phone had been
The data placed him near several of
the robberies when they happened. He was convicted
and sentenced to 116 years in prison.
And the police had gathered that 127-day map
without a warrant. They had not convinced
a judge that there was probable cause. They
had used a federal law that let them
get the records on a much weaker showing
— a standard far below the one the
Fourth Amendment usually demands. The reason they
were allowed to do that came from a
rule almost no one outside a courtroom had
ever heard of.
That rule is called the third-party doctrine, and
to understand Carpenter, you have to understand it.
In the 1970s, the Supreme Court decided a
pair of cases about information people had handed
to someone else — bank records in one,
the phone numbers a person dialed in another
The Court's logic was that once you
voluntarily give information to a third party —
a bank, a phone company — you have
given up your reasonable expectation of privacy in
it. You took the risk that they might
turn it over.
Remember the principle from our last episodes: privacy
is protected when society accepts your expectation as
reasonable. The third-party doctrine said that if you
shared the information, that expectation was gone. The
government could get it without a warrant, because,
in the eyes of the law, it was
no longer really yours.
In 1979, applied to a list of dialed
phone numbers, that idea was already aggressive, but
it was containable. A list of numbers
is thin. It does not tell you where
a person slept, who they visited, or whether
they went to a clinic, a church, or
a protest.
Cell-site records are different in kind, not just
degree. You do not choose to send
them. Simply by carrying a phone that is
turned on — which, in modern life, is
nearly everyone, nearly always — you generate a
continuous record of your location and hand it
to a company. There is no door
to close. There is no way to step
out of the booth. To opt out of
the tracking, you would have to disconnect from
modern life entirely.
And there is no realistic way out. You
cannot hold a job, raise a family, or
call for help in modern life without a
phone, and the moment it is on, the
tracking begins. The 1970s idea of voluntarily sharing
assumed a choice. Carrying a phone is not
a choice in that sense — it is
the price of admission to ordinary life.
So Carpenter's case forced a collision. On one
side stood a 1970s rule: share it, and
you lose it. On the other stood a
device that shares your location constantly, automatically, with
no real choice involved. If the old
doctrine applied, then the most detailed map of
your life ever created was available to the
government for the asking.
In 2018, by a vote of five to
four, the Supreme Court ruled for Carpenter.
Accessing his historical location records was a search
under the Fourth Amendment, and to get them,
the government generally needs a warrant.
Chief Justice John Roberts wrote the opinion, and
he was careful about how far it reached
The Court did not throw out the
third-party doctrine. It refused to extend it.
Cell-site location information, Roberts wrote, was a new
kind of record — a comprehensive, detailed, effortless
chronicle of a person's movements, reaching back through
time in a way that no traditional surveillance
ever could.
Two things made it different. First, the depth.
This was not a single trip or a
single call. It was a near-perfect record of
everywhere a person had been for months, revealing
the privacies of life — family, politics, faith,
health — through the simple fact of location
Second, the lack of real choice. You
do not meaningfully volunteer this information. It is
created automatically, just by keeping a phone on
The old idea that you "assumed the
risk" of sharing did not fit a record
you cannot avoid generating.
So the Court drew a line. When the
data is rich enough to map your entire
life, and you have no genuine way to
avoid creating it, sharing it with a company
does not strip away your privacy. The
government still needs a warrant.
The four dissenting justices warned that the Court
had opened a door it could not close
Where exactly is the line? How much
data is too much? Is location special, or
will the same logic eventually cover your emails,
your searches, your purchases? They argued the Court
had traded a clear rule for a vague
one, and that drawing these lines was a
job for legislatures, not judges.
The dissenters had a fair worry. A clear
rule, even an uncomfortable one, tells the police
exactly what they may do. A blurry line
invites years of new cases just to find
where it really falls — and until they
are decided, no one is quite sure.
They were not wrong that the line is
blurry. But the majority had decided that a
blurry line in the right place was better
than a clear rule in the wrong one.
Carpenter is the moment the Fourth Amendment stepped
into the smartphone era. For the first
time, the Court said plainly that digital data
can be so revealing that the old rules
simply do not fit it.
But notice what the decision did not do.
It did not say the government can never
see your data. It said that, for this
kind of record, it usually needs a warrant
— a judge, and probable cause. The
protection is real, and it is also narrow.
The Court deliberately limited the ruling to these
facts and left dozens of harder questions for
later.
And those questions are already here. Your location
is only one of the trails you leave.
There are records of what you search, what
you buy, who you message, and what your
devices sense around you. Each of those is
held by a third party. Each of them,
under the old doctrine, might be fair game.
Carpenter cracked that doctrine open for location data.
It did not resolve the rest.
That is the unfinished part. Carpenter answered the
question for location, but the same logic is
now knocking on every other door — your
searches, your messages, the quiet sensors in the
devices around you. Each new case will ask
the Court to decide, again, whether a record
you cannot avoid creating is still yours.
So the line we started drawing on a
Cleveland sidewalk is still moving. Every new device
asks the same question in a new form:
what have you truly kept private, when modern
life requires you to hand so much of
yourself to someone else just to function?
Three episodes, one question. On a Cleveland sidewalk,
the Court asked how much the police could
do to your body in public. With a
phone seized in an arrest, it asked whether
the device in your pocket was just one
more thing to search. And in Carpenter, it
asked whether a phone that tracks you every
minute could quietly erase everything the first two
cases had built.
The answer, so far, is that the Constitution
is still trying to keep up. The justices
who wrote these rulings could not have imagined
the phone in your pocket. They gave us
tools — reasonable suspicion, reasonable expectation, the warrant
— and left it to each new generation
to decide how those tools apply to machines
that did not exist when the words were
written.
That is the real story under all three
cases. The line between you and the people
who would watch you is not fixed. It
is argued, and redrawn, every time the technology
changes. And right now, that line runs straight
through the device you are probably holding to
watch this.