The police can take your car, your cash, even your house — and never
charge you with a crime .
They do it by accusing the property itself, not you.
For decades, in much of the country, there was almost no limit on how much
they could take.
Then, in 2019, one man's Land Rover — seized over a small drug case —
carried that question all the way to the Supreme Court .
This is the case that finally drew a line .
It is called civil asset forfeiture, and most people have never heard of
it until it happens to them.
It is not a fine handed down by a judge after a trial.
It is the government taking your property because it claims that property
was connected to a crime — sometimes without ever convicting you of
anything .
Over the next twelve minutes: how that system works, the man whose seized
SUV exposed its limits, and the centuries-old rule the Supreme Court
reached for to put the first real brake on it.
His name is Tyson Timbs, and his story starts with a loss.
When his father dies, Timbs receives roughly seventy-three thousand
dollars in life-insurance money.
With part of it, he buys a Land Rover SUV — about forty-two thousand
dollars .
He is also struggling.
Prescribed opioids for pain, he becomes addicted, and the addiction pulls
him toward heroin .
To feed it, he sells a small amount of heroin to undercover officers — a
few hundred dollars' worth.
He is arrested, and he does not fight the charge.
He pleads guilty .
Now notice what the court does with him as a person.
He is not sent to prison.
He is sentenced to home detention and probation, plus a little over a
thousand dollars in fees .
The system has looked at Tyson Timbs, weighed his crime, and decided he is
not someone to lock away.
But the state is not finished.
Separately, it moves to take the Land Rover — the
forty-two-thousand-dollar SUV he bought with his father's insurance money
.
And here is the number that makes the whole case.
The most Timbs could have been fined for his offense was ten thousand
dollars .
The car was worth more than four times that.
So a man who gets no prison time, for a small drug sale, stands to lose a
vehicle worth quadruple the maximum fine the law allows.
The trial court looks at that gap and says no — taking the car would be
grossly disproportionate to what he actually did.
It is, in plain terms, an excessive penalty .
That should have been the end of it.
It was only the beginning.
Because to take the car, the state was not really using the ordinary
criminal law at all.
It was using a separate, far older, and much stranger kind of power.
Civil asset forfeiture works on a legal fiction that sounds almost absurd
when you first hear it.
The case is not brought against the person.
It is brought against the thing .
That is why forfeiture cases have such peculiar names — the government
versus a car, versus a sum of cash, versus a house.
In the eyes of the law, the property itself is treated as the suspect.
And because the case targets the object, not the owner, the protections
you would expect in a criminal trial do not all apply.
In many places, the owner does not have to be convicted of a crime to lose
the property.
In some, they do not even have to be charged .
Think about what that means.
The whole weight of "innocent until proven guilty" is built around a
person.
Aim the case at an object instead, and that weight can quietly slip away.
Now, there is a reason this power exists.
Forfeiture grew as a tool to strip the profits out of organized crime and
drug trafficking — to take the boats, the planes, the cash that made the
crime worth doing.
Used that way, supporters argue, it disrupts criminal enterprises in a way
that arresting one person never could .
But critics point to what happens next, after the property is taken.
In many state systems, and in a federal program, the proceeds flow back to
the very agencies that seized the property .
The department that takes your car can, in effect, help fund itself with
it.
The Institute for Justice, the firm that took up Timbs's case, calls this
"policing for profit" — a built-in incentive to seize, regardless of guilt
.
This is not a left-or-right complaint.
Criticism of civil forfeiture runs across the political spectrum, from
civil-liberties groups to conservative reform groups, which is rare for
any issue in American law .
And yet, for years, one constitutional argument against it kept hitting a
wall — the very wall Tyson Timbs's case was about to break.
The argument was simple.
The Eighth Amendment to the Constitution forbids "excessive fines." If
taking a forty-two-thousand-dollar car for a crime with a
ten-thousand-dollar maximum fine is not excessive, what is?
The protection against excessive fines is one of the oldest in our legal
tradition.
Its roots reach back centuries, through English law all the way to Magna
Carta, which limited how harshly the crown could fine a person for an
offense.
The Supreme Court treated this as a right deeply rooted in the nation's
history — not a modern invention .
But there was a catch, and it is a technical one that decided everything.
For most of American history, the Bill of Rights restrained only the
federal government.
Over the twentieth century, the Court "incorporated" most of those
protections — applied them to the states, one by one, through the
Fourteenth Amendment.
The question in Timbs was whether the ban on excessive fines had ever been
formally applied to the states at all.
Indiana's Supreme Court had said no — and used that gap to uphold taking
the car .
In 2019, the Supreme Court closed the gap.
By a unanimous vote — nine to nothing — it held that the Excessive Fines
Clause does apply to the states, just like the rest .
The opinion was written by Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg.
A protection that old, she reasoned, that fundamental, could not possibly
bind only the federal government while leaving every state and city free
to impose fines without limit .
The justices were so united that the only disagreement was about the
route, not the result.
Justices Gorsuch and Thomas agreed the clause applies to the states, but
argued it should get there through a different part of the Fourteenth
Amendment .
On the core point, there was no dissent at all.
But read the ruling carefully, because the Court was careful.
It did not declare that taking Timbs's car was unconstitutional.
It did not abolish civil forfeiture .
It did something narrower and, in a way, more durable: it sent the case
back to Indiana and held that, from now on, the question of whether a
forfeiture is an excessive fine is a real constitutional question the
states have to answer .
So Timbs is a limit, not an ending.
Civil forfeiture still exists.
Police can still seize property.
What changed is that there is now a constitutional ceiling — a principle
that the punishment, including the value of what is taken, cannot be
grossly out of proportion to the offense, in any courtroom in the country
.
And for Tyson Timbs himself, the story has an ending most of these cases
never get.
Back in Indiana, after years of litigation, the courts finally applied
that principle and let him keep his car .
The Land Rover his father's death had paid for stayed in his hands.
But step back from the one car.
The deeper power has not gone away.
Every day, property is seized across the country on the theory that the
object, not the owner, is the wrongdoer .
Timbs gave people a tool — a way to argue that a seizure is simply too
much — but you have to know the tool exists, and you have to be able to
fight for years to use it.
Most people cannot.
That is the quiet truth under the case.
A constitutional limit is only as strong as the people who can afford to
invoke it.
The line exists now.
Whether it protects you depends on whether you can reach it.
We have spent three episodes on what the state can see of you — your
street, your phone, your movements.
This is a different question.
Not what they can watch, but what they can take .
And Timbs is the moment the Court said that even here, where the case is
aimed at a thing instead of a person, there is a line that a fine — or a
forfeiture — cannot cross .
It took a man, a Land Rover, and a rule older than the country to draw it.
But property is not only what you can carry or drive.
What happens when the thing the government wants is the ground under your
feet — your home — and it wants to hand that home to someone else
entirely?
The Constitution says the government can take private property for "public
use." The next case asked the most dangerous question hiding in those two
words: what counts as public use?
That is next time.