It is a weekend. You are not at school. You are on your
own phone, and you post something — angry, crude, the
kind of thing teenagers post when they are upset . Can
your school punish you for that? In 2021, a
fourteen-year-old's disappearing Snapchat reached the
Supreme Court of the United States, and the answer it
gave shapes the rights of every student — and every
parent — in the age of the phone .
Students do have free speech. A famous 1969 case said
so: young people do not "shed their constitutional
rights at the schoolhouse gate" . But schools can still
limit speech that seriously disrupts the school. For
decades, that line was easy to draw, because school
speech happened at school. Then everyone got a phone,
and the gate disappeared. Now a student's words can be
posted from a bedroom at midnight and be in front of the
whole school by morning. Over the next twelve minutes:
the post, the punishment, and the moment the Court had
to decide where a school's power over your voice
actually ends.
Her name is Brandi Levy. In 2017 she is fourteen, a
student at Mahanoy Area High School in Pennsylvania, and
a cheerleader — on the junior varsity squad .
She wants to be on varsity. She does not make it. She is
told to stay on JV, while a younger student moves up. To
a fourteen-year-old, this is not a small thing; it
stings .
So, on a Saturday, off school grounds, at a local
convenience store, she does what a lot of frustrated
teenagers do. She opens Snapchat, takes a photo of
herself and a friend with their middle fingers raised,
and adds a caption — short, blunt, and full of
profanity, aimed at school, at softball, at cheer, at
everything . We are not going to repeat it, but you can
imagine the energy of it: pure, unfiltered teenage
anger.
Here is the thing about Snapchat. The post is supposed
to vanish. It goes out to her friends — about two
hundred and fifty of them — and then it is gone . But
"gone" is a myth. Someone takes a screenshot. The
screenshot travels. And it lands exactly where she least
wants it: in front of the cheerleading coaches .
And it is worth sitting with how ordinary this was. No
threat. No named target. No plan. Just a teenager, off
the clock, cursing her own disappointment into a phone —
the most forgettable kind of speech there is, until a
screenshot made it permanent .
The school's response is firm. For that post — made on a
weekend, off campus, on her own phone — Brandi is
suspended from the junior varsity cheerleading team for
the entire upcoming year .
To the school, this is simple discipline: a cheerleader
publicly trashing the program she is part of. To Brandi
and her parents, it is something else: a public school
reaching off campus, into a weekend, to punish a
teenager for words it did not like. They sue,
represented by the ACLU, and the question rides all the
way up to the Supreme Court .
To understand the stakes, you have to go back to that
1969 case, Tinker v. Des Moines. Students had worn black
armbands to school to protest a war, the school punished
them, and the Supreme Court sided with the students .
Tinker set the rule that still governs student speech.
Yes, students have First Amendment rights. But a school
can discipline speech that would "substantially disrupt"
the school — that genuinely interferes with running it.
Armbands worn silently did not cross that line. A
protest that shut the school down might .
Those students had worn the armbands in 1965 to mourn
the dead of the Vietnam War, after the school banned
that specific protest in advance. The Court's answer was
blunt: neither students nor teachers shed their
constitutional rights at the schoolhouse gate — but a
school may still act when speech would substantially
disrupt its work .
For fifty years, that test worked, because it had a
place. School speech meant speech at school — in the
hallway, the classroom, the assembly. A school's
authority had edges you could see.
The phone erased those edges. When a student can
broadcast to the entire school from her own bedroom, at
any hour, on any day, what counts as "school speech"? If
a school can punish a disruptive post made off campus,
then in principle it can reach a student's words
twenty-four hours a day, anywhere — because almost
anything a student says online could, in theory, ripple
back to school .
And that is the quiet danger the case exposed. Not that
schools would punish one rude Snapchat, but that the
logic for punishing it had no natural stopping point.
Follow it far enough, and a student never really leaves
school at all. The gate that Tinker assumed — the line
between the school's world and the rest of a young
person's life — had simply dissolved.
In 2021, the Supreme Court ruled for Brandi Levy. By a
vote of eight to one, it held that the school had
violated her First Amendment rights when it punished her
for that off-campus post .
Justice Stephen Breyer wrote the opinion, and his
reasoning was careful. A school's special authority over
what students say, he explained, is weaker off campus
than on. Off campus, a student is normally in the care
of her parents, not the school. And if schools could
police student speech around the clock, that power would
reach so far into private life that it could swallow
students' free speech entirely .
Breyer added a thought that explains why the Court bent
toward the student. America's public schools, he wrote,
are the "nurseries of democracy" — the place a free
society teaches the next generation to tolerate the
speech it dislikes. A school that punishes every
unpopular off-campus word does not model that lesson; it
teaches the opposite .
The Court also looked at what had actually happened, and
found almost nothing. Brandi's post had caused, at most,
a few minutes of discussion in one class. That is not
the "substantial disruption" Tinker requires. The school
had punished frustration, not chaos .
But — and this is the part people miss — the Court
refused to give students a blank check. It pointedly did
not say that schools can never reach off-campus speech.
It listed the kinds of things that might still justify a
school stepping in, even off campus: serious bullying or
harassment aimed at other students, threats, cheating,
breaking real rules. It declined to draw one bright
line, leaving the hard cases for later .
One justice would have gone the other way. Justice
Clarence Thomas dissented, arguing that historically
schools had broad authority over students that did
extend beyond the campus, and that the majority was
discarding that tradition . His was the lone vote. But
it points at the real difficulty: nobody, including the
Court, drew a clean line — because in the age of the
phone, a clean line may not exist.
So where does this leave you, or your kid? With a
protection that is real but deliberately fuzzy. After
Mahanoy, a public school cannot punish a student simply
for an ordinary, off-campus, online vent that does not
disrupt the school . Frustration on a weekend is not the
school's business.
But it is not a wall. The same ruling keeps the door
open for the serious cases — the threat, the targeted
harassment, the cheating ring run over a group chat .
The result is a gray zone that every student and parent
now lives in, decided post by post, case by case.
And notice what the Court actually protected. Not a
noble political statement, but a crude, throwaway
Snapchat that vanished in seconds. That was on purpose.
The Court understood that free speech is tested not by
the speech we admire, but by the speech we find petty,
or rude, or pointless — because that is the speech the
powerful are most tempted to punish.
A fourteen-year-old's bad weekend, captured in a
disappearing post, ended up drawing one of the most
important lines of the smartphone era: the line between
the school's authority and the rest of a young person's
life . The school could reach a lot. It could not reach
everything.
We have now watched the state try to search you, track
you, and take your property — and try to police what you
say. In every one of those fights, the pattern is the
same: a power that made sense in a smaller world,
stretched by technology until a court has to find its
edge again. And every time, that edge looks less like a
fence than a line drawn in pencil — ready to be moved by
whatever device comes next.
But not every right is taken from you by a school or a
police officer. Some you hand over yourself — willingly,
in seconds, without reading a word. The next case is
about the most common contract in modern life, the one
you agree to constantly, that quietly signs away your
right to ever take a company to court.
That is next time.