You are arrested.
Before you are even in the car,
an officer reaches into your pocket and takes
out your phone — your messages,
your photos, your location, the record of
almost everything you do .
Can the police simply open it and start
reading?
For most of the smartphone era,
the answer was unclear.
Then, in 2014, the Supreme Court gave an
answer so blunt it became famous: if the
police want to search your phone,
get a warrant .
For two hundred years, the law had a
simple rule: when the police arrest you,
they can search what is on you —
your pockets, your wallet, whatever you are
carrying — without a warrant .
It made sense when "what you are carrying"
meant a few objects.
But the device in your pocket is not
an object.
It is a window into your entire life.
Over the next twelve minutes: the traffic stop
that put that question in front of the
Supreme Court, and the moment the Court
decided that a smartphone is different from
anything a person has ever carried before.
In 2009, a man named David Riley is
pulled over in San Diego,
California.
The initial reason is ordinary: he is driving
on a suspended license, and his car is
going to be impounded .
When officers search the car,
they find firearms hidden inside.
Riley is arrested.
And during that arrest, an officer takes the
smartphone out of his pocket and begins
looking through it .
What the officer finds goes far beyond the
traffic stop.
There are photos, videos, and contacts on the
phone, and some of them appear to connect
Riley to a street gang and to an
earlier shooting .
Later, at the station, a detective goes
through the phone again, in more detail,
building a case from what is stored inside
it.
None of this is done with a warrant
.
Using the evidence from the phone,
prosecutors charge Riley in connection with
the shooting — a far more serious matter
than how he was first stopped .
Riley's case travels to the Supreme Court
alongside a second one, very different on the
surface.
A man named Brima Wurie is arrested in
a drug case, and police use the call
log on his simple flip phone to find
an address .
One case is a modern smartphone,
the other an old flip phone.
Together, they force the Court to answer a
single, growing question: when the police
arrest you, is the phone in your pocket
just one more thing they are allowed to
search?
To see why this was hard,
you have to understand a rule called "search
incident to arrest."
For a long time, the courts have allowed
police, when they make a lawful arrest,
to search the person and the area within
their reach — without a separate warrant .
The reasons are practical.
First, officer safety: the police need to make
sure you are not reaching for a weapon.
Second, preserving evidence: they need to stop
you from destroying something before it can be
collected .
Under that rule, courts had upheld searches of
the things people carry — a wallet,
a pocket, a crumpled cigarette package.
So the government's argument in Riley was
straightforward.
A phone, it said, is just another item
found on the person during an arrest.
If the police can look inside a wallet,
why not the phone next to it?
But the Court looked harder at what a
phone actually is.
A wallet holds a few cards and photos.
A modern smartphone holds tens of thousands of
messages, years of photographs, a browsing
history, a calendar, location records,
and access to even more data stored in
the cloud .
The two are not the same kind of
thing, the Court said — not in how
much they hold, and not in what that
holding reveals.
And much of what a phone reaches is
not even stored on the phone.
Tap an app and you may be looking
at data that lives on a company's servers,
somewhere else entirely.
By 2014, searching the device could quietly
become a search of a life that is
kept half in your pocket and half in
the cloud .
And the old justifications did not fit.
The data inside a phone cannot be used
as a weapon; it cannot cut an officer
or help a suspect escape .
The fear of evidence being destroyed could be
handled in other ways, like securing the
device.
Strip away those two reasons,
and what was left was simply the government
wanting to read a person's entire digital
life, on the spot, because they happened to
be under arrest.
In 2014, the Supreme Court ruled,
and not one justice dissented .
The opinion was written by Chief Justice John
Roberts, and its core was simple: the police
generally may not search the digital contents
of a cell phone seized during an arrest
without a warrant .
Roberts wrote that modern phones are now such
a pervasive and insistent part of daily life
that they hold, in digital form,
the privacies of life .
The sum of an individual's private life can
be reconstructed from the device — where they
have been, who they know,
what they believe, what they fear.
A search of a phone,
he said, is not like emptying a pocket.
Roberts pushed the point further.
A search of a phone,
he wrote, is not just larger than a
search of a wallet — it can be
more revealing than the most thorough search
of a house.
Your home does not carry a record of
everywhere you have been, everything you have
searched for, and every message you have ever
sent.
The phone in your pocket does .
The Court did not say the police can
never see what is on your phone.
It said they have to do what the
Constitution normally requires for something
this private: go to a judge,
show probable cause, and get a warrant .
The ruling came down to three words that
are now quoted constantly: get a warrant .
This was not a brand-new idea.
It rested on a principle the Court had
set out decades earlier, in a case about
a man in a phone booth.
There, the Court had held that the Fourth
Amendment protects people, not places — that
what you reasonably try to keep private stays
protected, even out in the world .
Riley took that principle and carried it into
the smartphone.
Your phone is not a place the police
have walked into.
It is the most concentrated record of you
that has ever existed.
It is also why the Court took two
phones, not one.
Riley's was a modern smartphone; Wurie's was a
basic flip phone.
By deciding them together, the justices made
clear the rule was not about how advanced
your device is.
The protection attaches to the phone as a
category — the thing almost everyone now
carries — not to the model in your
hand .
The Court left one important door open.
In a true emergency — a bomb,
a kidnapping, a child in danger — the
police can still act without waiting for a
warrant .
The rule protects your phone.
It does not turn it into a shield.
Riley was the first time the Supreme Court
looked squarely at the smartphone and said:
this changes things .
The old rules, written for pockets and
wallets, could not simply be stretched over a
device that holds your entire life.
But notice how careful the ruling is.
It protects the contents of the phone —
the messages, the photos, the files you can
see when you unlock it.
It assumes the private thing is the data
you put there on purpose.
And it still leaves room for emergencies,
for consent, and for the warrant the police
can always go and get .
Think about what is actually on the device
the Court was protecting.
Not only photos and messages,
but the apps that quietly reveal the most
private corners of a life — what you
pray to, who you love,
what illness you are reading about at two
in the morning.
The Court did not need to catalog every
one.
It only had to see that,
taken together, they add up to you .
What it does not fully answer is the
harder question hiding underneath.
Your phone does not only hold what you
choose to put in it.
Just by being on, it is constantly creating
new information about you — and handing it
to someone else.
Every few minutes, it tells the nearest tower
where it is.
You never type that.
You never see it.
And it does not stay in your pocket
— it goes straight to your phone company.
Riley protected what is inside the device.
The next case would ask who owns the
trail the device leaves behind.
David Riley's case began with a traffic stop
and ended with a rule that touches everyone
who carries a phone.
After 2014, the most personal object most
people own could not be cracked open by
the police just because they had been
arrested.
For that, the police need a warrant .
But the protection had an edge to it.
It guarded the words and images you placed
inside the phone — the things you knew
were private.
It said much less about the information the
phone produces on its own,
automatically, and sends away without asking
you.
And the most revealing of all those automatic
records is location.
Your phone keeps a quiet,
continuous log of where you are,
day and night, and stores it with your
carrier.
If the police want that map of your
life, do they need a warrant — or
did you give it away the moment you
turned the phone on?
In 2018, the Court finally answered.
That is next time.