The government can take your home.
Most people know that
for a highway a school
a bridge. But what if it
takes your home in perfect
condition having done nothing wrong and
hands the land to a private developer
In 2005 a woman's small pink house
in Connecticut put that exact
question in front of the
Supreme Court. The answer
changed what two words
in the Constitution are allowed to mean.
The power is called eminent domain.
The Fifth Amendment lets the
government take private property
but only for public use and only if it
pays you a fair price.
For most of history public use meant
something the public actually uses a road
a reservoir a courthouse.
Kelo v. New London asked whether
those two words could stretch
to cover something else entirely taking
working-class homes and giving the
land to private business in the hope
of jobs and taxes.
Over the next twelve minutes
the neighborhood that was erased
the 5-4 decision that allowed it
and the spectacular way it backfired.
The place is New London
Connecticut a small
city on the water and the
neighborhood is called Fort Trumbull.
It is not rich but it is real modest
homes some lived in for generations.
One of them belongs to Susette Kelo.
It is a small house she
has fixed up and painted a
distinctive pink with a view of the water.
She has done nothing wrong.
Her home is not
run-down. There is no crime scene here
no blight no code violations.
But the city has a plan.
The pharmaceutical company Pfizer
is building a large research
facility nearby and New London wants to
capitalize on it to remake the whole Fort
Trumbull area with offices a hotel
and upscale housing that would
bring in jobs and tax revenue.
To do it the city works through
a private nonprofit acting
as its development agent the New
London Development Corporation.
And that agency is given the
power to do something dramatic
to use eminent domain to
condemn the homes in Fort
Trumbull to force the
owners to sell whether
they want to or not.
Susette Kelo and a handful
of neighbors refuse.
They are not holding out for more money.
They simply do not want to
lose their homes so that
someone else can build something
more profitable on the land.
So they sue represented
by a public-interest law
firm the Institute for Justice and their
fight climbs all the way
to the Supreme Court.
And the question they bring
is deceptively simple.
The Constitution allows
takings for public use.
Is handing your home to
a private developer for a
plan that might create
jobs really a public
use Or has the city
just found a way to take
from one private owner and give to another
To see why this was so hard
you have to look closely
at the words themselves public use.
Read narrowly public use means the
public gets to use the
thing you can drive on the
road drink from the reservoir walk into
the courthouse. Under that reading taking
homes to hand to a private company fails
because the public will
not own or use the new
development private parties will.
But over the twentieth
century courts had read those
words more and more
broadly as public purpose.
Under that reading a taking
is fine as long as it
serves some public benefit
even if a private party
ends up with the property.
Clearing genuine slums for example
had been upheld on that logic.
New London's argument leaned
entirely on the broad reading.
The city was not claiming
Fort Trumbull was a slum.
It was claiming that
economic development itself
more jobs more taxes a
revitalized waterfront
is a public purpose and
therefore a public use.
If the Court accepted that the
implications were enormous.
Almost any home anywhere
could be taken and handed to a
developer as long as a
city could claim the new
use would generate more
economic activity than the
old one. A modest house almost always
produces less tax revenue than offices or
luxury condos. Under the broad reading
that gap alone could justify taking it.
So the case was never
really about one pink house.
It was about whether
the words for public use
still set any limit at all on whose
property the government
can transfer to whom.
In 2005 the Supreme Court
sided with the city.
By a vote of five to four
it held that taking the
Fort Trumbull homes for the
economic-development plan
did count as a public use
under the Fifth Amendment.
The opinion was written by
Justice John Paul Stevens.
The Court did not say the
homes had to be blighted.
It said that a carefully considered
economic-development plan aimed
at public benefits like jobs
and revenue qualifies as a public purpose
and that courts should largely
defer to a city's judgment
about what its community needs.
Public use in other words would
be read as public purpose.
One vote in the majority
came with a caveat.
Justice Kennedy who
joined the Court's opinion
wrote separately to
stress that a taking meant
only to benefit a particular private party
with a merely pretextual public purpose
would still be unconstitutional leaving a
door however narrow for future challenges.
The four dissenters were alarmed.
Justice Sandra Day O'Connor
wrote the main dissent
and her warning was blunt.
Under this ruling she
argued the government could
now take property from one private owner
simply to give it to another who
might use it more profitably.
The specter she wrote was
that any home could be taken
for any other private
use that promised more
taxes and that the words for public
use had in effect been
erased from the Constitution.
Justice Thomas wrote a separate
dissent arguing the Court had
drifted far from the original
meaning of the clause.
It was a 5-4 split and unlike many such
splits it did not fall
along the usual lines.
That is part of why what
happened next was so unusual.
Because the public reaction
to Kelo did something
American legal decisions almost never do
it united nearly everyone against it.
The ruling set off one
of the largest popular
backlashes to any modern
Supreme Court decision
and a rare bipartisan one.
People across the political
spectrum recoiled at the idea
that the government could
bulldoze your home to make way
for a more profitable private
project. And legislatures responded.
In the years after Kelo
by the Institute for
Justice's count roughly
forty or more states
passed new laws or
constitutional amendments
restricting the use of eminent
domain for economic development.
The catch and it is an important one
is that many of these
reforms were later criticized
as weak full of loopholes that
left the core power largely intact.
Passed a reform did not always
mean actually protected homeowners
But the sharpest verdict on Kelo
came not from a legislature.
It came from the land itself.
After the homes of Fort
Trumbull were taken and
demolished the grand
redevelopment was never built.
The promised offices and
hotel did not appear.
The cleared land sat
empty year after year.
And then the final irony.
In 2009 Pfizer the company
whose arrival had justified the whole plan
closed its New London facility and left.
The neighborhood had been erased
for a development that never
came to serve a company that did not stay.
For a long time the most
famous use of the bulldozed
land was as a place to dump storm debris.
And it is worth being precise
about what taken meant
for the people who lived there.
Some families had been in
Fort Trumbull for generations.
They were paid the market
value of their homes as the
Constitution requires but market
value does not buy back the
place you have lived your whole
life or the neighbors who scatter
once the bulldozers arrive.
That the dissent had warned was the human
cost the broad reading
made easy to ignore.
Susette Kelo's house at least survived.
It was not destroyed
it was carefully taken
apart and moved piece by piece to a
new lot elsewhere in New
London where it stands today
as a small monument to the fight.
She does not live in it anymore.
Kelo is still good law.
The Supreme Court has never overturned it.
What pushed back against it
was not the Court but the
country the backlash the state
reforms and the empty
lot that made the human
cost impossible to ignore.
And that is the strange
lesson of the case.
The Constitution's limit for public
use was read so broadly that it
stopped doing much work.
What replaced it was
not a better legal rule
but public outrage and
an embarrassing failure
on the ground. We have
now followed the state as
it reaches for your body your phone
your movements your property and your home
the things it can watch
and the things it can take.
But there is one more kind
of power and it is the
most personal of all.
Not what the government can
take from you but what it
can stop you from saying.
The next case begins with
a teenager a few words
and a question every student
and worker eventually
asks where does your right to speak
actually end That is next time.