You get arrested.
Maybe it is serious, maybe it is a mistake —
it does not matter yet,
because you have not been tried,
let alone convicted.
And during booking, an officer runs a cotton swab along
the inside of your cheek,
reads your DNA, and enters your genetic code into a
national database that is searched against unsolved crimes .
In 2013, by a single vote,
the Supreme Court said they are allowed to do that.
The Fourth Amendment is supposed to stop the government from
searching you for evidence of a crime unless it has
a specific reason to suspect you of that crime .
But there is an exception built into being arrested: the
booking process, where the police fingerprint you and
photograph you to confirm who you are.
The question in this case was whether a DNA swab
belongs in that box —
a routine way to identify you —
or whether it is something else: a search of your
body for evidence of crimes no one has accused you
of.
Over the next twelve minutes: the cheek swab,
the cold case it cracked,
and the deep, unusual split it caused.
In 2009, a man named Alonzo King is arrested in
Maryland.
The charge is assault —
he had menaced a group of people with a shotgun
.
That arrest is based on its own facts; it has
nothing to do with what follows.
During booking, under a Maryland law,
the police take a cheek swab and record his DNA
.
This is the key detail to hold onto: the swab
is not why he was arrested.
It is a routine step the state applies to people
arrested for serious crimes.
His DNA profile goes into the database.
And there, it matches genetic evidence left at the scene
of a rape from 2003 —
a case that had gone unsolved for years .
On the strength of that match,
King is charged with that rape,
and he is convicted of it .
So look at what just happened from two different angles,
because the whole case lives in the gap between them.
From one angle: a violent crime that had gone cold
for six years was finally solved,
and a rapist was held accountable,
because of a swab taken at booking.
From the other angle: the government took a sample of
a man's body —
before he had been convicted of anything —
and used it to search for his connection to an
entirely different crime he was not suspected of .
Both descriptions are true.
That is what makes the case hard.
To decide it, the Court had to answer a deceptively
simple question: what is a DNA swab,
legally?
Is it more like a fingerprint,
or more like a search?
Think about what already happens when you are booked.
The police take your fingerprints and your photograph.
Courts have long allowed this,
because its purpose is identification —
confirming that the person in the cell is who they
say they are, and checking whether they are wanted elsewhere
.
It is not treated as a search for evidence,
because that is not really what it is for.
The state argued DNA is just the next step in
that same process —
the fingerprint of the twenty-first century.
A cheek swab is quick and barely physical.
And like a fingerprint, the state said,
it identifies the arrestee, and it can be checked against
records —
including the records of unsolved crimes .
But critics, and four of the justices,
saw a sleight of hand in that word "identification." A
fingerprint taken at booking is mostly used to confirm who
you are right now.
DNA, in practice, was being used for something different: to
run the arrestee against a national database of crime-scene
evidence, looking for hits .
That database has a name —
CODIS, the FBI's national DNA index —
and the whole value of swabbing arrestees comes from
searching it against cold cases .
If that is the purpose,
the dissent argued, then it is not really "identification"
at all.
It is a search of your body for evidence of
crime —
exactly the thing the Fourth Amendment normally forbids
without individualized suspicion .
There was also a quieter worry underneath.
A fingerprint reveals almost nothing about you except its
own pattern.
DNA is different —
it is a blueprint that can expose your relatives,
your health, your most private traits.
The majority stressed that the law used only a narrow
set of identifying markers, not your whole genome.
Critics answered that the physical sample itself is kept,
and that the line the state draws today,
it can quietly move tomorrow .
In 2013, the Supreme Court upheld the swab.
By a vote of five to four,
it held that taking a DNA cheek swab from someone
arrested for a serious offense,
as part of routine booking,
is a reasonable search under the Fourth Amendment .
The opinion was written by Justice Anthony Kennedy.
The intrusion, he reasoned, is minimal —
a brief, gentle swab of the cheek.
And the government's interests are strong: identifying who
is in custody, knowing their history,
and the broader public-safety value of the DNA system.
Weigh the small intrusion against the large interest,
the majority concluded, and the swab is reasonable.
It is, in the Court's words,
like fingerprinting and photographing —
a legitimate booking procedure .
Kennedy also spelled out what "identification" meant to the
majority, and it was broader than a name.
Knowing an arrestee's full history,
the Court said, helps officers judge how dangerous he might
be, whether he is a flight risk,
and whether he threatens the people around him.
DNA, in that view, was not a fishing expedition —
it was part of safely processing a person already in
the state's custody .
The dissent was sharp, and it came from an unusual
place.
Justice Antonin Scalia wrote it —
and he was joined not by his usual allies,
but by three of the Court's liberal justices,
Ginsburg, Sotomayor, and Kagan .
When the most conservative and the most liberal justices
line up together, it is worth paying attention.
Scalia's argument was direct.
The swab, he said, was not really about identifying Alonzo
King —
the police already knew who he was.
Its purpose was to investigate unsolved crimes,
and the Constitution does not allow the government to search
a person for evidence of crime without a reason to
suspect them of it .
And he ended with a warning that has been quoted
ever since: as a consequence of this decision,
he wrote, your DNA can be taken and entered into
a national DNA database if you are ever arrested,
rightly or wrongly, and for whatever reason.
He felt strongly enough that he read a summary of
his dissent aloud from the bench —
something justices do only for the rulings they most oppose
.
So here is where it leaves you.
In much of the country,
being arrested for a serious offense now means giving a
DNA sample —
taken before any trial, kept in a database,
and searched against unsolved crimes .
The exact rules vary from state to state,
but the principle the Supreme Court blessed is the same
everywhere.
And the honest truth is that both sides of this
were right about something real.
The system genuinely works: DNA databases have closed cold
cases, freed innocent people, and identified violent
offenders who would otherwise have walked free .
That is not a small thing.
But it is also true that the people swept into
those databases include the merely arrested —
people charged with something and later cleared,
people arrested by mistake —
whose genetic code is now on file because of a
single encounter with the police .
That is the trade the Court made,
by one vote: a powerful tool against serious crime,
paid for with the genetic privacy of everyone an officer
decides to arrest.
Whether that trade is worth it is exactly the kind
of question the Constitution is supposed to answer —
and here, it split the Court down the middle,
across every usual line.
A cheek swab taken at a booking desk solved a
six-year-old crime —
and, in the same motion,
redrew the line around the most personal thing you own:
the code inside your own cells .
The Court called it a fingerprint.
Four justices called it a search.
The difference between those two words is the difference
between identifying you and investigating you.
We have followed the state as it reaches into your
pockets, your phone, your property,
your contracts, and now your body.
Each time, a power that began small is stretched to
fit a world the founders never saw —
and each time, a court has to decide how far
is too far.
But there is one place that has always been the
strongest fortress of all —
the one the law guards most jealously,
where you are supposed to be safest from the state:
your own home.
So what happens when a police officer,
chasing you for something minor,
follows you right up to your door —
and you step inside?
Can they come in after you,
without a warrant?
That is next time.