You are walking down a sidewalk when a police officer stops you, turns you
around, and runs
his hands along the outside of your clothes. He has no warrant. He has not
seen you commit
a crime . Most people assume that is illegal. It is not. The rule that allows
it was written
in 1968, and it began with one detective watching two men pace in front of a
store window .
This is the case that drew the line between a hunch and proof.
We think of the Fourth Amendment as a simple wall: the police need a warrant,
or at least solid
evidence, before they can search you. For most of American history, that was
close to true.
But there is a gap in that wall, and almost every street stop in the country
now passes through
it . Over the next twelve minutes: the ordinary afternoon that created the
gap, the standard
the Supreme Court invented to fill it, and the quiet cost of letting suspicion
— not proof
— put a hand on your shoulder.
It is October 1963, in downtown Cleveland, Ohio. A plainclothes detective
named Martin McFadden,
thirty-nine years on the force, is watching the street the way he has watched
it for decades
.
He notices two men. One walks down the block, pauses at a particular store
window, looks inside,
and walks on. A short distance away he turns, comes back, and looks into the
same window again.
Then the second man does exactly the same thing. Back and forth, the two of
them, about a dozen
trips in all — five or six times apiece .
To most people on the sidewalk, this is nothing. To McFadden, it is a pattern
he recognizes.
Men do not usually study a single store window a dozen times in the middle of
the afternoon.
He believes he is watching two men case a robbery — checking the layout, the
register, the
way out .
He has not seen a crime. He cannot point to stolen goods or a weapon in plain
view. What he
has is experience and a strong suspicion. Under the ordinary rule, that is not
enough to search
anyone.
McFadden approaches the men, identifies himself, and asks for their names.
They mumble a reply.
And now he has a decision to make. If these men are about to rob a store, at
least one of them
may be carrying a gun. If he is wrong, he is about to put his hands on
innocent people for
no legal reason.
He spins one of the men, John Terry, around and pats the outside of his coat.
He feels the
shape of a pistol. He reaches in and takes it out. A second pistol comes off
the other man
.
Terry is charged with carrying a concealed weapon . And his case exposes a
problem the law
had been avoiding for a long time.
The Fourth Amendment protects people against "unreasonable searches and
seizures." By 1963,
the usual test for a search was demanding: an officer needed probable cause —
a fair, fact-based
belief that a specific crime had been committed — and often a warrant signed
by a judge.
Detective McFadden had none of that. He had not watched a robbery happen. He
had watched two
men look in a window. If the court measured his pat-down against the full
probable-cause standard,
the gun was an illegal search, and under the rule from our last episodes, the
evidence would
be thrown out.
But push the other way, and a different danger appears. Police officers
approach suspicious
people every day, long before a crime is complete. If an officer can never
check a person for
a weapon until he already has proof of a crime, then the most dangerous moment
of the job —
the unknown person, the unseen gun — is also the moment the law leaves him
most exposed.
So the question that reached the Supreme Court was narrow and uncomfortable.
Is there a kind
of police contact that sits below a full arrest — a brief stop, a quick check
for weapons —
that the Constitution should allow on less than probable cause? Or does
opening that door hand
the police a tool they will use on anyone, for almost any reason?
The Court understood both sides of that question. It knew the streets were
real, and so was
the temptation to abuse a softer rule. The decision it wrote in 1968 tried to
hold both truths
at once, and that is exactly why it has been argued about ever since.
In 1968, by a vote of eight to one, the Supreme Court upheld the search . The
opinion was written
by Chief Justice Earl Warren — the same Court that, in these same years, was
expanding the
rights of suspects across the country . That detail matters. This was not a
Court looking for
ways to help the police. It was a Court that decided the street was a genuine
exception.
The Court built its answer in two parts. First, the stop. An officer may
briefly stop a person
when he can point to specific, describable facts that make him reasonably
suspect that crime
is afoot . Not a hunch he cannot explain — facts he can lay out later, the way
McFadden could
describe the pacing and the window.
That phrase — specific and articulable facts — is doing quiet, heavy work. It
means an officer
cannot simply say a person looked suspicious and leave it there. He has to be
able to name
what he saw and explain why it added up. McFadden could: two men, the same
window, a dozen
trips, their heads together between each pass. Reasonable suspicion is not a
feeling the officer
has; it is a story he can tell afterward, in specific terms, that a judge can
test .
Second, the frisk. If, during that stop, the officer reasonably believes the
person may be
armed and dangerous, he may run his hands over the outer clothing — and only
the outer clothing
— to check for weapons . The purpose is narrow: not to find evidence, but to
make sure no one
gets shot during the encounter.
And the Court drew that limit tightly. A frisk is not a license to empty your
pockets. It is
a pat-down of the outer clothing, feeling for the hard shape of a weapon —
nothing more. If
an officer goes further, reaching in to explore for something that is plainly
not a weapon,
he has crossed the line the Court drew and stepped back into the world that
needs probable
cause and a warrant . The whole point was to give an officer just enough, and
not one inch
more.
The Court was honest about what this was. A stop is a seizure. A frisk is a
search . It did
not pretend otherwise. It simply held that this limited kind of search could
be reasonable
on a lower standard than probable cause — a new standard the law now calls
reasonable suspicion
. With that, the gun found on Terry was allowed to stand .
One justice refused to go along. William O. Douglas warned that the Court was
giving an officer
on the street a power that even a judge did not have — the power to seize and
search a person
without probable cause. To loosen the rule below probable cause, he wrote, was
a long step
down a dangerous road . His was the single dissenting voice. But it would echo
for the next
half-century.
The "Terry stop" became one of the most common encounters between police and
the public in
America . Every day, officers stop people on a standard that is real but
blurry: facts that
add up to reasonable suspicion.
The strength of the rule is also its weakness. "Reasonable suspicion" depends
on judgment,
and judgment can be sharpened by training — or bent by bias. In the decades
after Terry, some
cities used the stop-and-frisk power so heavily that it became the center of a
national argument
about who gets stopped, and how often, and why .
Picture how that plays out now. An officer does not need to watch you commit a
crime. He needs
a handful of facts he can later put into words — where you were, what you did,
how it fit a
pattern he has seen before. On a good day, that is careful police work
stopping a real threat
before it happens. On a bad day, the same low bar can make being stopped feel
less like an
event and more like weather .
That argument is not really a disagreement about the 1968 ruling. The Court
was careful. It
demanded specific facts, not vague feelings, and it limited the frisk to a
search for weapons.
The problem is what happens when a careful rule meets the pressure of a quota,
a bad assumption,
or a long day on a hard street.
And so Terry leaves us with a permanent tension. We want officers to be able
to protect themselves
in the seconds before they know who they are dealing with. We also do not want
suspicion alone
to be enough to stop and handle anyone, anywhere. The line between those two
things is thin,
and it is redrawn on sidewalks every single day.
Terry v. Ohio answered a question about the street: how much can the police do
to your body,
in public, on less than proof. The detective watched two men, named a real
suspicion, and the
Court let the gun stand .
But almost everything in that case depended on being out in the open — on a
man the officer
could see, on a sidewalk anyone could walk down. The Fourth Amendment grew up
protecting physical
things: your house, your pockets, the ground you stand on.
So what happens when the police do not want what is in your pockets, but what
is on the device
inside them? When the thing they reach for is the phone that holds your
messages, your photos,
your whole life? The next time the Court faced that question, it had to decide
whether the
rules built for pockets and coats could possibly fit a computer that fits in
your hand.
That is next time.